RG 069:158, Ruth Baker Stephan Collection of WWII Letters
Connecticut State Library
Ruth Baker Stephan Collection of World War II letters
1927-1964
bulk 1941-1947
Connecticut State Library
Stephan, Ruth Baker
3 cubic feet
The collection consists primarily of correspondence between Ruth Baker Stephan and military service members of St. Paul’s United Methodist Church of Hartford during World War II. Photographs, publications, and Stephan’s personal papers are also included.
RG069_158
2011-084
Biographical Note
Mary E. Baker gave birth to Ruth Edgerton Baker on March 3, 1917. Ruth E. Baker grew up in West Hartford, Connecticut. She was a member of St. Paul's United Methodist Church on Park Street in Hartford, Connecticut. Ruth Baker married John Edmund Stephan on October 9, 1943. During World War II, she wrote monthly newsletters from the Wesleyan Service Guild to military service members of her church. She worked at Highland Dairy, the Life Insurance Research Bureau, and the accident department of Travelers Insurance.
Scope and Content
The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence and photographs received by Ruth Baker Stephan from military service members of St. Paul's United Methodist Church of Hartford during World War II. The collection also contains monthly newsletters that Stephan wrote as a part of the Wesleyan Service Guild of St. Paul's Church. The collection is arranged into 6 series:
Series 1. Correspondence, 1941-1948, undated, consists of all of the correspondence sent to Stephan from members of St. Paul's United Methodist Church during and after the war. There are also approximately 40 returned letters that were sent by Stephan and a folder of empty envelopes. In the correspondence the church members describe life in the military, talk about hometown news, and respond to questions and/or requests from Stephan's newsletters. All correspondence within the U.S. military was first approved by censors, as a result many of the war-time letters lack specifics that can be found in later post-war correspondence.
Series 2. Wesleyan Service Guild, 1941-1947, contains all of the copies of Stephan's newsletters; address cards and notes; St. Paul's Methodist Honor Roll list; and a St. Paul's Church bulletin.
Series 3. Personal Papers, circa 1927-1943, consists of Stephan's fifth grade history report of West Hartford, Stephan's 1941 salary receipts, an invitation to an insurance company anniversary dinner, and a copy of a newspaper article covering Stephan's wedding.
Series 4. Publications, 1945-circa 1964, undated, contains several newspaper clippings regarding members of St. Paul's Church. In addition, the series includes copies of The Hartford Courant.
Series 5. Photographs, 1942-1947, undated, includes photographs of service members of St. Paul's Methodist Church, as well as places they visited abroad.
Series 6. Artifacts, 1944-1945, one handkerchief found in a Christmas card from Stephan and duplicates of poem cards.
Series 7. Restricted, 1941-1963, undated, contains newspapers and clippings that are restricted due to condition.
Arrangement
Arranged in seven series:
Series 1. Correspondence, 1941 - 1948, undated, arranged chronologically with undated folders at the end of the series.
Series 2. Wesleyan Service Guild, 1941 - 1947, arranged chronologically.
Series 3. Personal Papers, circa 1927 - 1943, arranged chronologically.
Series 4. Publications, 1945-circa 1964, undated, arranged chronologically.
Series 5. Photographs, 1942-1947, undated, is further arranged into the following subseries: People and Scenes. The people are arranged alphabetically by last name with unidentified people at the end.
Series 6. Artifacts, 1944-1945, arranged chronologically.
Series 7. Restricted, 1941-1963, arranged chronologically.
Index Terms
Persons:
Stephan, Ruth Baker
Places:
Hartford (Conn.); West Hartford (Conn.)
Subjects:
World War, 1939-1945; Connecticut -- History; Protestants -- Connecticut; Women in the Methodist Church; Methodist Church; Methodist Church -- Connecticut -- Hartford
Document Types:
Clippings; Personal correspondence; Photographs; Newspapers; Notes; Church bulletins; Newsletters
Restrictions on Access
Series 7. Restricted, 1941-1963, undated, is restricted due to condition. Contact State Archives staff for assistance.
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Provenance
The Ruth Baker Stephan Collection of WWII letters was donated by Arline M. Stephan to the Connecticut State Library in December, 2010.
Container List
- Series 1. Correspondence, 1941-1948, undated
  - Correspondence, 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 1-18)
  - Correspondence, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 1-13)
  - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 1-16)
  - Correspondence, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 1-15)
  - Correspondence, 1946-1948, undated (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
  - Empty envelopes, 1943-1944, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Series 2. Wesleyan Service Guild, 1942-1947, undated
  - Address cards, 1943-1945, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Address notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Newsletters, 1942-1947 (Box 5, Folder 8-13)
  - St. Paul's Church bulletin, 1944 February 6 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - St. Paul's honor roll, 1943 May 12 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Series 3. Personal papers, circa 1927-1964
  - Personal papers, circa 1927-1943 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Series 4. Publications, 1945-circa 1964
  - Clippings, 1946, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Publications, 1945-circa 1964 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Series 5. Photographs, 1942-1947, undated
  - People
    - Bacon, William, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Bartlett, William Francis, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Berriman, Thomas Henry, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Chisholm, Robert, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Dammiller, George, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Evans, Albert G., undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Field, Kenneth, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Hilson, Fred, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Laporte, Chester, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - M[ ], Herb, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - MacD., D. Ellis, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Five untitled photographs - Margaret, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - McAllister, Don, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - McAllister, Sue, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - McAllister, Sue, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Cedar Falls, Iowa - McAllister, Sue, 1943 August 8 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - [Mc]Kinney, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Roberts, A.W., undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Meno Park [et al] - Saxton, Bill, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - (Mother and I) - Schroeder, Catherine, 1942 July 5 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Silvay, undated (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Smith, Lloyd Orin, undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Whiteley, [Don], undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Wickham, Ray, undated (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Ziegler, Melvin P., undated (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Two out-of-focus photographs with re-take slip, undated (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Unidentified men, undated (Box 6, Folder 27-55)
    - Unidentified woman - "St. Augustine", 1943 March (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - Unidentified woman, undated (Box 6, Folder 57)
    - McAllister, Sue, undated (Box 6, Folder 63)
    - Roberts, Amy, undated (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - Scenes
    - The Ernie Pyle Building, 1947 January 20 (Box 6, Folder 58)
    - The San Shin Building, 1947 January 20 (Box 6, Folder 59)
    - WAVE Quarters "G" - Florida Hall, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 60)
    - Three untitled photographs of "Natives" - Saxton, Bill, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 61)
    - View from plane, undated (Box 6, Folder 62)
- Series 6. Artifacts, 1944-1945
  - Artifacts, 1944-1945 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Series 7. Restricted, 1941-1963, undated
  - Clippings, 1946, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Military Base Newspapers, 1943-1945 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Newspapers, 1941-1954 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Newspapers, 1958-1963 (Box 7, Folder 4)